Chapter 29 enter Ahab to him stub.
Some days elapsed and ice and icebergs all a stern. The peekquad now went
rolling through the bright keto spring, which at sea almost perpetually reigns
on the threshold of the eternal august of the tropic. The warmly cool, clear,
ringing, perfumed, overflowing, redundant days, were as crystal goblets
of Persian sherbet heaped up, flaked up with rosewater snow. These starred and
stately knights seemed hotty dames in jeweled velvets, nursing at home in
lonely pride the memory of their absent conquering earls, the golden helmeted
sons. For sleeping man, it was hard to choose between such winsome days and
such seducing nights. But all the witcheries of that unwaning weather did
not merely lend new spells and potencies to the outward world. Inward they turned
upon the soul, especially when the still mild hours of Eve came on. Then memory
shot her crystals as the clear ice most forms of noiseless twilights. And all
these subtle agencies more and more they wrought on Ahab's texture.
Old age is always wakeful, as if the longer linked with life, the less man
has to do with ought that looks like death. Among sea commanders, the old
greybeards will often leave their births to visit the nightcloak deck. It was so
with Ahab, only that now of late he seemed so much to live in the open air
that truly speaking his visits were more to the cabin than from the cabin to the
planks. It feels like going down into one's tomb, he would mutter to himself,
for an old captain like me to be descending this narrow scuttle to go to my gravedoug birth.
So almost every 24 hours, when the watches of the night were set, and the
band on deck sentinelled the slumbers of the band below, and when, if a rope was
to be hauled upon the folks, the sailors flung it not rudely down, as by day, but
with some cautiousness dropped it to its place for fear of disturbing their
slumbering shipmates. When this sort of steady quietude would begin to prevail,
habitually these silent steersmen would watch the cabin scuttle, and heirlong
the old man would emerge, gripping at the iron banister to help his crippled
way. Some considering touch of humanity was in him, for at times like these he
usually abstained from patrolling the quarter deck, because to his wearied
mates seeking repose within 6 in of his ivory heel, such would have been the
reverberating crack and den of that bony step that their dreams would have been
on the crunching teeth of sharks. But once the mood was on him too deep for
common regardings, and as with heavy lumberlike pace he was measuring the
ship from taff rail to main mast, Stub, the old second mate, came up from below
with a certain unassured deprecating humorousness, hinted that if Captain
Ahab was pleased to walk the planks, then no one could say nay, but there
might be some way of muffling the noise, hinting something indistinctly and
hesitatingly about a globe of toe in the insertion into it of the ivory heel. Ah,
Stub, thou did not know Ahab. Then am I a cannonball, Stub, said Ahab, that thou
wst wad me that fashion. But go thy ways I had forgot. Below to thy nightly
grave, where such as ye sleep between shrouds, to use you to filling one at
last. down, dog and kennel."
Starting at the unforeseen concluding exclamation of the so suddenly scornful
old man, Stub was speechless for a moment, and then said excitedly,
"I am not used to being spoken to that way, sir. I do, but less than half like
it, sir." "Avast," gritted Ahab between his set teeth, and violently moving away
as if to avoid some passionate temptation.
No, sir, not yet, said Stub, emboldened.
I will not tamely be called a dog, sir.
And be called 10 times a donkey and a mule and an ass, and be gone, or I'll
clear the world of thee. As he said this, Ahab advanced upon him with such
overbearing terrors in his aspect that Stub involuntarily retreated.
I was never served so before without giving a hard blow for it, muttered Stub
as he found himself descending the cabin scuttle. It's very queer. Stop stub.
Somehow now I don't well know whether to go back and strike him or what's that
down here on my knees and pray for him?
Yes, that was the thought coming up in me. But it would be the first time I
ever did pray. It's queer. Very queer.
And he's queer, too. I take him for and after. He's about the queerest old man
Stub ever sailed with. How he flashed at me. His eyes like powder pans. Is he
mad? Anyway, there's something on his mind as sure as there must be something
on a deck when it cracks. He ain't in his bed now either, more than 3 hours
out of 24, and he don't sleep then.
Didn't that doughboy, the steward, tell me that of a morning he always finds the
old man's hammock clothes all rumpled and tumbled, and the sheets down at the
foot, and the cover lid almost tied into knots, and the pillow a sort of
frightful hot, as though a baked brick had been on it? A hot old man. I guess
he's got what some folks assure call a conscience. It's a kind of tick dolly
row, they say. Worse, nor a toothache.
Well, well, I don't know what it is, but the Lord keep me from catching it. He's
full of riddles. I wonder what he goes into the afterhold for every night as
Doughboy tells me he suspects. What's that for? I should like to know. Who's
made appointments with him in the hold.
Ain't that queer now? But there's no telling. It's the old game. Here it goes
for a snooze. Damn me, it's worth a fella's while to be born into the world,
if only to fall right asleep. And now that I think of it, that's about the
first thing babies do. And that's sort of queer, too. Damn me. But all things
are queer, come to think of them. But that's against my principles. Think not
is my 11th commandment. And sleep when you can is my 12th. So here goes again.
But how's that? Didn't he call me a dog?
Blazes. He called me 10 times a donkey and piled a lot of jackasses on top of
that. He might as well have kicked me and be done with it. Maybe he did kick
me and I didn't observe it. I was so taken all back with his brow somehow. It
flashed like a bleached bone. What the devil's the matter with me? I don't
stand right on my legs. Coming a foul of that old man has a sort of turned me
wrong side out. By the lord, I must have been dreaming though. How? How? How? But
the only way is to stash it. So, here goes to hammock again. And in the
morning, I'll see how this plaguy juggling thinks over by daylight.